Guide to the Henry R. Dwire Papers, 1897-1944
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Henry R. Dwire papers 1897-1944
University Archives, Duke University
Dwire, Henry R.
1.2 Linear Feet 250 Items
Henry R. Dwire was an alumnus of Trinity College and was appointed Duke University Vice President in 1941 and Director of Public Relations and Alumni Affairs in 1944.
The collection includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, certificates and a diploma. The collection ranges in date from 1897-1944.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Henry R. Dwire Papers were received by the University Archives as transfers in 1960, 1971, and 1976.
Biographical Note
Henry Rudolph Dwire was born in Winston-Salem, NC on October 8, 1882 to Henry Xenophon and Mary Hanes Dwire. He graduated from Trinity College with the A.B. degree in 1902 and with the M.A. degree in 1903. During his senior year, he was editor of The Archive. In 1904, Dwire became editor of the Twin City Sentinel, published out of Winston-Salem, and became known as one of the State's best-known editorial writers. During his lifetime, Dwire served on the Winston-Salem School Board and was a trustee for the North Carolina State Hospital for the Insane. He founded the Winston-Salem Fine Arts Foundation and in 1931 was director of the North Carolina Art Society. Dwire held State appointments under four successive North Carolina Governors and was a member of the State School Commission. He was managing editor of The South Atlantic Quarterly and editor of The Duke Alumni Register. He was director of the Duke University Press, University Vice President (1941) and Director of Public Relations and Alumni Affairs (at the time of his death) and served on numerous University committees. He was a member of Alpha Tau Omega, Omicron Delta Kappa, and Phi Beta Kappa. Davidson College awarded Dwire an Honorary Doctorate of Laws degree in 1943. He died in July 1944.
Collection Overview
The collection contains Dwire's high school diploma, two certificates, correspondence, photographs, and clippings. The correspondence is congratulatory towards Dwire for his appointment as Duke University Vice President in 1941 and for the honorary degree he was awarded by Davidson College in 1943. Most of the photographs were taken at Davidson College. Most of the loose material was removed from a scrapbook after being transferred to the Archives in 1960. There is adhesive on many of the pages. The collection ranges in date from 1897-1944.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Dwire, Henry R.
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--History -- 20th century
Duke University -- History -- 20th century
Duke University -- Administration
Duke University. Dept. of Alumni Affairs
Duke University. Office of the Vice President
Davidson College (N.C.)
Winston-Salem (N.C.)
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
Photograph Collection, 1861-2006
Duke University Archives
Holton (Holland) papers, 1859-1956
Duke University Archives
University Treasurer (Office of) records, 1893-1979
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Certificate, the National Society of the Sons of the American Revolution, 1942
  - Certificate, Dwire's appointment to the N. C. State Board of Education, 1943
  - Scrapbook pages, unbound, contain clippings about Dwire's death, 1944
  - Photographs of Dwire
  - Crowell letter, 1930
  - Correspondence, 1936
  - Correspondence, 1940-1941
  - Correspondence, 1943
  - Clippings and Programs, 1903, 1941, 1943
  - Diploma, Winston [N.C.] City Schools, 1897